Paolo Tamagnini

paolotamag.github.io twitter.com/paolotamag linkedin.com/in/paolo-tamagnini-2490433a

Data scientist with research experience, fond of interactive data visualization for complex problems, data evangelist in the open source space, aware of pros and cons of both scripting and UI-based ML platforms. **Keywords**: visual programming, visual analytics, data science, eXplainable AI, Python, KNIME, d3.js

EXPERIENCE

KNIME Berlin, Germany

Senior Data Scientist, Evangelism Team

May. 2018 - present

Email: paolotamag@gmail.com

Mobile: +39 333 496 4088

- Evangelism through the KNIME Educators Alliance: Since May 2023 I have been scouting and supporting academics and lecturers for the KNIME Educators Alliance. Besides supporting them in their teaching, I am also managing special collaborations by integrating requested functionalities in KNIME via components and workflows. This required to translate the academics abstract ideas into precise requirements, then implement these on the fly.
- Building Data Science Apps via Visual Programming: Since May 2021, through the maintenance of a JIRA board and Confluence pages, I have been coordinating a team of volunteers (mostly KNIME data scientists and solution engineers) to build, verify, document and publish (via monthly releases) Verified Components. Sometimes scripting in JavaScript, Python and R is required. The apps I personally build are around those topics: guided/visual analytics, autoML, human-in-the-loop, MLOps, active learning, weak supervision and explainable/responsible AI.
- Evangelism and Upskilling via Articles, Conferences and Social Media: Since May 2018 I have been working within the Evangelism team to create contents on different formats for external and internal channels: data science online magazines, business conferences, meetups and webinars. Find links on my my website. During 2021 and 2022 I led the upskilling sub-team through a Trello board, supporting junior hires in the usual evangelism activities, scouting and reviewing Community Components Collections shared by the open source KNIME community, regardless of whether they are partners, customers or simply KNIME fans.
- Gartner Magic Quadrant and Forrester Wave: In 2018, 2019 and 2020 I supported the leadership team in preparing the briefings for external reports such as <u>Gartner</u> and <u>Forrester</u> which review and benchmark KNIME software in comparison with other vendors.

New York University, Tandon School of Engineering

Brooklyn, NY

Research Intern

Aug. 2016 - Nov. 2017

• Developing Machine Learning Applications in Python and JavaScript: Working as a research intern in the team of Prof. Enrico Bertini we developed two XAI tools Rivelo and a Python package partial_dependence. I presented both of them at a Google NYC Research Seminar.

EDUCATION

Sapienza University of Rome

Rome, Italy

Two-year M.Sc. in Data Science; GPA: 4.00 (110 cum laude / 110)

Oct. 2015 - Oct. 2017

• The first master in Italy for data science: Studied topics were: machine learning, statistical and bayesian inference, cloud computing and more. Most of the projects were coded in *Python* or *R* and they are all uploaded to my <u>GitHub</u>. I graduated in October 2017 being part of the first graduation of data science in Italy with important guests from companies and institutions like Google, Eurostat, Unicredit and more.

Sapienza University of Rome

Rome, Italy

B.Eng. in Management; GPA: 3.89 (107 / 110)

Oct. 2012 - Oct. 2015

• A bachelor covering basics of most scientific and business areas: This course helped me to find my love for data and taught me to be flexible to many different domains.

Programming Skills

• Languages: Python, d3.js, R, SQL, HTML, CSS // Tools: KNIME, quick learner of other workflow-based frameworks

PUBLICATIONS

• Interpreting Black-Box Classifiers Using Instance-Level Visual Explanations:

P. Tamagnini, J. Krause, A. Dasgupta and E. Bertini. In Workshop HILDA co-located with SIGMOD 2017.